A Guide to the Atcheson L. Hench Autograph Collection
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Atcheson L. Hench Autograph Collection
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6435,etc
The collection consists of ca. 870 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The majority of the collection, which consists of accessions MSS 6435,-a, was given to Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, on December 30, 1960 and November 27, 1961. Hench continued to donate additions to the autograph collection during his lifetime through MSS 6435-bg and MSS 6435-bi. MSS 6435-bh was given by bequest through his estate on August 23, 1974.
Biographical/Historical Information
Atcheson Laughlin Hench (1891-1974), Linden Kent Memorial Professor Emeritus of English at the University of Virginia, was born in Orange, New Jersey, and grew up in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, attending college at Lafayette College in Easton, Pennsylvania, in 1912. He received both his Master's (1917) and Doctorate (1921) degrees from Harvard University, before he began his teaching career as an associate professor at the University of Virginia in 1922. Hench was to remain at the University for forty years, becoming a full professor in 1925 and the Linden Kent Memorial Professor in 1940. Also in 1925, he married Virginia Bedinger Michie (d. 1971), and they had two daughters, Margaret Hench Underwood and Clare Showalter Hench.
Dr. Hench was a member of the Phi Beta Kappa and the Raven Society, and received the Algernon Sydney award I 1966. He was well-known for his work as a consultant in compiling dictionaries, contributing to the Oxford English Dictionary, and served as a frequent contributor and editor of American Speech. He also served as a visiting professor at the New York University and a Fulbright Lecturer at the University of Innsbruck, Austria. His interest in local history and public affairs was reflected in his presence on the Charlottesville School Board and his contributions to the Magazine of Albemarle County History. Hench was well-known for his varied and wide interests and everyone who knew him seems to have their own favorite Hench stories.
Scope and Content
The Atcheson L. Hench Autograph Collection consists of material collected by Hench, ca. 870 items (12 Hollinger boxes, 5 linear feet), from the mid 9th century to the 20th century, some for an autograph collection and others for use in his classes at the University of Virginia with examples of various periods.
The collection includes material reflecting his interest in Old English, Middle English and Elizabethan script; letters by associates of Edgar Allan Poe; Civil War letters; papers relating to Virginia history; correspondence of writers, poets, politicians, and other correspondence, including both American and English literary and historical material. People with significant amounts of material associated with their name include George Cary Eggleston, Paul Hamilton Hayne, William Ernest Henley, William Cabell Rives, and Edmund Clarence Stedman.
Many of the descriptions of items in Box 1 benefited from the expertise and notes of Consuelo Dutschke who examined these documents in 2007.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in two series: Series I: Medieval and Early European Manuscripts (Boxes 1-6) and Series II: Collection of Modern Autographs (Boxes 7-12). Longer runs of correspondence (like Paul Hamilton Hayne) are arranged as usual under the name of the writer, then alphabetically by name of the recipient, with the letters to unidentified recipients or simple autographs arranged chronologically after the identified ones.
Contents List
- Series I: Medieval and Early European Manuscripts
  - [mid 9th to 10th c.] Sacramentale, two separate Latin fragments on vellum in Carolingian script, Hench # 1.c (6435-a) (Box-folder 1:1)
  - c. 1175 Psalter with commentary, written in a late Carolingian minuscule, three columns to a page with text in center column, numerous smaller initials in red, vellum, Northern France, 1 leaf, Hench # 1.a (6435-a) (Box-folder 1:2)
  - 12th century Leaf from Latin Bible, portions of Deuteronomy XIII-XVI, glossed in pregothic script, with large green, blue, and red colored initials, identified by English calligrapher, M.R. Gullick, as a mid-12th century Cistercian manuscript from Germany, on vellum, Hench #1.j (6435-a) (oversize)
  - c. 1220 the Venerable Bede, Fragments from De Temporibus - De Temporum Ratione, containing the complete text of chapter XVII, Gothic script, written in Germany, vellum, double columns, with 36-37 lines to the column, one page with a large initial "D" in green, blue and red with interlace work and extending into the margin showing a dragon-like creature, and also on the same page showing three original holes in the parchment, two leaves, Hench #1.e (6435-a) (Box-folder 1:3)
  - c. 1250-1300 Breviary fragment, five leaves, on vellum, Gothic minuscule in two columns with 52 lines to the page, rubricated with initials in red and blue, Hench #1.g (6435-a) (Box-folder 1:4)
  - 13th century Fragment of the Decretum Gratiani, portion of Book II, 23, vellum, rubricated with traces of blue in the initials, Hench # 1.d (6435-a) (Box-folder 1:5)
  - c. 1300 Three large fragments in Latin of a theological nature, written in England, vellum, possibly clipped for use by a book binder, with some red paragraph marks, Hench # 1.i (6435-a) (Box-folder 1:6)
  - c. 1350 Fragment of the Life of Saint Wenceslaus on vellum, written in Bohemia, double columns, rubricated with some initials touched with red, recto blurred, Hench # 1.h (6435-a) (Box-folder 1:7)
  - c. 1375-1399The Pricke of Conscience by Richard Rolle of Hampole,; English cursive book hand; initial pages missing; undecorated catchwords on unnumbered leaves, decorated catchword at end of quire; 1st leaves in quire numbered; frame ruled in crayon, bound in brown Morocco gilt with gilt edges, on vellum (Vault, Medieval Mss E)
  - 14th century One leaf from Missal, on vellum, two columns of 27 lines each, in Latin, written in Gothic script, letters in brown ink, two capitals in blue and red, two in gold, one gold ornament down the margin, some red scroll work, England, Hench # 8 (6435-a) (Box-folder 1:8)
  - 14th-15th century Contract, written in cursive Gothic script, on vellum, in law French, concerning a hospital and containing many Latin phrases, England, Hench # 2.b (6435-a) (Box-folder 1:9)
  - 1412 Deed for Property in Hawkhurst, Kent, England, in Latin, vellum, one leaf, Hench # 2.a (6435-a) (Box-folder 1:10)
  - [1437] May 30 Fragment of a Document signed by Humphrey Stafford (1402-1460), 1st Duke of Buckingham, vellum, 1 page, Hench # 6 (6435-a) (oversize)
  - 1441/42 October 12 Deed or Charter, Cecilia Sharp to William March[we?] and William Aston, granting a tenement in the parish of All Hallows Barking, London, next to the Tower of London, vellum, in Latin, in Gothic script, Hench #7 (6435-a) (Box-folder 1:11)
  - c.1460-1470 Probably from a Book of Hours, parts of the suffrages of Barbara and Mary Magdalene, Oracio, rubricated with illuminated letters in gold with blue and green ornaments, vellum, England, 1 leaf, Hench # 1.b (6435-a) (Box-folder 1:12)
  - 15th century (2nd half) Two leaves from a miniature Book of Hours, probably Flemish, written on thin vellum in liturgical black letter, one page with large illuminated "D" and floral border with acanthus leaf motif, both with decorated capitals in gold, blue and red for the opening of the Seven Penitential Psalms, Hench # 1.f.2 (6435-a) (Box-folder 1:13)
  - 15th century One leaf from a notated breviary, written on vellum in liturgical black letter and decorated with alternating red and blue pen work initials, of French origin, with square musical notes on red four-line staves, Hench # 1.f.1 (6435-a) (Box-folder 1:14)
  - 15th century Pseudo-Seneca, De remediis fortuitorum, preceded by Gasparinus Pergamensis, De arte punctuandi, vellum, Italian, in Humanistic script, bound in 18th century blue morocco with gilt, with the bookplate of Henry Alan and A.N.L. Munby, has one large initial of animal drawings of a goose and wyvern, ff. 1-6; ff.6v-7v ruled but blank; item is also on microfilm M-2333, Hench # 9 (6435-a) (Box-folder 1:15)
  - 1502 A French legal document involving the honorable Guillaume Duhamel and Jehan Lebondau the younger, on vellum, 1 page (6435-ar) (oversize)
  - [1510-1550?] Two large folio sheets, four pages each, removed from a Choir Book, early 16th century, Florence, Italy, Roman script with some initials and words in red, on vellum, Hench #1 .k (6435-a) (oversize)
  - [ante 1536] Commonplace Book of Robert Sherborne (d. 1536), Bishop of Chichester, 158 pages on paper bound together with a much later paper wraparound cover, containing various memoranda, notes on places mentioned in scripture, and sermon notes, with the autograph signature of Sherborne on the first page, includes possibly later additions in another hand, Hench # 20 (6435-a) (Box-folder 1:16)
  - [1543 August 24] Charterhouse Charter, granting to Sir John Nevyll, Knight, the Mansion House and tenement situated at the east end of the Churchyard of the Carthusians; a 17th Century copy for Sir Thomas Pryde and Mr. Thomas Pardey, 34 pages, attached at top by a vellum cord, on paper, Hench # 16 (6435-a) (oversize)
  - 1560 Legal document, probably a lawsuit, 2 vellum pages fastened with together with a small cord, Hench # 13 (6435-a) (Box-folder 1:17)
  - 1562 Ecclesiastical Census of England and Wales compiled by Laurence Nowell (ca. 1515-1571), antiquarian, on paper; ff. 36; limp vellum binding, Hench # 3 (6435-a) (Box-folder 1:18)
  - 1564 April 11 French [legal document?] on vellum, purchased from Paul C. Richards in 1970 (6435-ao) (Box-folder 1:19)
  - 1568History of the Dukes of Normandy by William of Jumiege in the hand of Laurence Nowell, marginal notes and index in the hand of his student, William Lambarde (1536-1601), in Latin, 80 pages; unidentified armorial bookplate, Hench # 4 (6435-a) (Box-folder 1:20)
  - 1572De necessariis observantiis scaccarii dialogus ("Dialogue of the Exchequer") by Richard Fitzneale (ca. 1130-1198), and English bishop and Treasurer of England under Henry II and Richard I, in the hand of a professional scribe, with marginal annotations by William Lambarde, 137 pages, on paper, bound in 19th c. calf gilt, ruled in red with the arms of the fourth Duke of Newcastle on upper cover, Hench # 10 (6435-a) (Box-folder 1:21)
  - 1574Liber Niger Domus Edward IV, an account of the household establishment of Edward IV, in Latin, written in the hand of antiquarian William Lambarde, on paper, bound in 17th c. calf re-backed, 293 pages, with additional pages of an alphabetical index; somewhat damaged from mold stains and damp (Phillips MS 12414), Hench # 11 (6435-a) (Box-folder 2:1)
  - 1576 June 1 Letter from William Lambarde to Sir Henry Sidney (copy), 4 pages on paper, dedicating his Topographical Dictionary [Perambulation of Kent: Containing the Description, Hystorie and Customs of the Shyre] to Sidney, Hench # 5a.9 (6435-a) (Box-folder 2:2)
  - [1585] Hand-written transcriptions on paper of William Lambarde's letter to the Lord Treasurer containing reasons why her Majesty should with speed embrace the action of the defense of the Low Countries, 3 copies of different dates and in different hands, Hench # 5a.9 (6435-a) (Box-folder 2:3)
  - 1589 October 21 Instructions for the sale of Her Majesty's lands, in the hand of William Lambarde, 3 pages on 1 l., on paper, Hench # 5a.3 (6435-a) (Box-folder 2:4)
  - ca. 1589 "Instructions for keeping a court-baron or a court leet" in the hand of William Lambarde, 4 pages on 2 l., on paper, Hench # 5a.2 (6435-a) (Box-folder 2:5)
  - [1591] Indenture of Thomas Duddeley, William Lambarde, and Thomas Wigges, in Latin on vellum with seals, Hench # 12.a (Box-folder 2:6)
  - 1593 January 5 Legal Document, vellum, concerning Rich Langford of Whitechurch signed by John Glanvyle and William Grymes, Hench # 13 (6435-a) (Box-folder 2:7)
  - 1593 July 11 Brief Document of Nathaniel Bacon (1547-1622), Sheriff of Norfolk, in a small Elizabethan hand, 1 page, on paper, Hench # 19 (6435-a) (Box-folder 2:8)
  - 1596 December 3 Legal document, vellum, concerning an obligation of the executors of Henry Warren to pay a sum of fifty pounds to Richard Hale, currently [residing?] at the home of Humfrey Walcott, Hench # 13 (6435-a) (Box-folder 2:9)
  - [1596] Indenture of William Lambarde, Thomas Fortescue, and Thomas Wigges, in Latin, on vellum with seals, concerning land in Kent, mentions William Cecil and Sir John Fortescue, Hench # 12.b (6435-a) (Box-folder 2:10)
  - 1597 May 25 Receipt from John Willard of Grays Inn and William Lambarde of Lincoln's Inn and his wife for the purchase of the farm called Clerke's lying in Leigh and Tonbridge, Kent, 1 page, on paper, Hench # 53 (6435-d) (Box-folder 2:11)
  - 1599 Legal document, possibly a property conveyance from Robert [Welles], on vellum, with the signatures of Henry Miles, Ed[ward?] Webb, and Hra: Crawley on the back, 3 pages on 1 l., on paper, Hench # 14 (6435-a) (Box-folder 2:12)
  - 16th century A Brief, listing a series of complaints against [Richard] Carmarden of London, Surveyor of the Customs to Queen Elizabeth, and the damage caused by his misbehavior to shipping, trade, and receipt of customs, Hench # 5a.7 (6435-a) (Box-folder 2:13)
  - 16th century The humble petition of the gentry, ministry, and commonalty of Kent to the honorable House of Commons, chiefly in the hand of William Lambarde, Hench # 5a.1 (6435-a) (Box-folder 2:14)
  - late 16th century Legal document on vellum, containing two distinct items in two different hands, one at least written during the reign of Elizabeth I, and both concerning the family of Edward Wharton of [Milton?], Hench # 13 (6435-a) (Box-folder 2:15)
  - [16th-17th century] Unidentified Legal document, 1 page, on vellum, Hench # 13 (6435-a) (oversize)
  - 1600 April 5 John Kynd to William Lambarde concerning the constables of Blackheaths Hundred, 1 page on paper, Hench # 5.a.4 (6435-a) (Box-folder 2:16)
  - [ante 1603] October Indenture during the reign of Queen Elizabeth I, involving Elizabeth and Thomas [Pryott] of Stratton, 2 pages on paper, with seal attached with a vellum "ribbon,", Hench # 13 (6435-a) (oversize)
  - 1603-1604 Account book, on paper stitched together without a cover, containing the signature of Gabriel Greene, Hench # 13 (6435-a) (Box-folder 2:17)
  - [1607 May 5] Indenture involving John Yardley, Robert and Elizabeth Yardley, and John Mirholl, signed by Richard Yardley at the bottom of the 1 page, paper document, Hench #14 (6435-a) (oversize)
  - 1609 June 6 Indenture, with decorated first initial, between James [Field?] of Kent County, James Andrewes, and William [?], damaged on right side with an attempted repair, vellum with partial seal on vellum "ribbon", Hench # 13 (6435-a) (oversize)
  - 1611 October [17th?] Francys Partlett to Sir Nathaniel Bacon of Stiffkey, Norfolk, writes that he is unable to answer the complaint of Thomas Holdenby against him on the day appointed by Bacon because he must appear before the King's Auditor at Thetford that same day to give account of the rents and revenues collected from the dissolved monastery of Westerham, 1 page on paper, Hench # 15 (6435-a) (Box-folder 2:18)
  - 1614 August [31?] Indenture between Thomas Parker of Maidstone, Kent County, and Robert [Keyes?], of Kent County, 1 page on vellum, with decorated first initial, large seal on vellum "ribbon", Hench # 14 (6435-a) (oversize)
  - 1615-1616 Legal document concerning the administration of the Thomas Daw[es?] Estate signed by Edmundus Woodhall Registrarius, on vellum, Hench # 13 (6435-a) (Box-folder 2:19)
  - 1616 February 12 Speech of Sir John Manson at the King's Bench Bar, 3 pages on 1 l. on paper, Hench #5.a.10 (6435-a) (Box-folder 2:20)
  - 1619 July 31 Indenture between Edward Thruxton and Joane Thruxton, 1 page, on paper, Hench # 14 (6435-a) (Box-folder 2:21)
  - [ante 1623?] "Sententiae Alphabeticae" Compilation of Latin, Greek, French and English Proverbs and Miscellany, contains the signature of [a former owner?] John Seaman on page 137, paper pages, formerly bound in a brown cover, but currently with one loose and separated cover and the other cover missing, Hench # 17 (6435-a) (Box-folder 2:22)
  - ca. 1623-1629 Notebook containing chiefly sermon notes but also some medical and logic notes in Elizabethan script, on paper, bound with 19th century boards with a calf backstrip and corners, with the name William Bury written on inside cover, Hench #21 (6435-a) (Box-folder 2:23)
  - 1627-1755 Legal documents, bonds, and indentures of the Warcupp Family, sewn together as a group, on paper, Hench # 18.b (6435-a) (Box-folder 3:1)
  - 1628 Speech addressed "To my Noble Friends in the lower house of Parliament," unknown author, on paper, with the number 52 written on the first page, Hench # 22 (6435-a) (Box-folder 3:2)
  - ca. 1645-1658 Notebook kept by a young French Jesuit student, possibly under the authority of Julien Haineuve (1588-1663), in French, 81 numbered pages bound in a small book, with green cover, Hench # 26 (6435-a) (Box-folder 3:3)
  - 1648 September 30 Legal document of William Snall giving Power of Attorney to his friend, Gilbert Hall of Lynton, Kent to enter into a [rental agreement?] with John Parker and William Parker for a tenement, garden and orchard in Kent, on vellum, Hench # 14 (6435-a) (Box-folder 3:4)
  - 1649-1692 "Purchases of Inheritance and M.[E?] Lambarde's Leases Thereof," on paper, Hench # 5a.5 (6435-a) (Box-folder 3:5)
  - 1650 December 14 Deed between John Wells and Solomon and Joseph Sibley of London, on vellum, Hench # 14 (6435-a) (Box-folder 3:6)
  - 1654 December 1 Will of George Warcupp, a London merchant, in Elizabethan hand, 2 pages on 1 leaf, on paper, Hench # 18.a (6435-a) (Box-folder 3:7)
  - 1657 August 14 Indenture made before the hundred court of [Dover?] before the Mayor Thomas White, involving Nathaniel Smith, John [?] and his wife, Katherine, and Richard Barclay, among others whose names are illegible, on vellum, Hench # 13 (6435-a) (Box-folder 3:8)
  - 1659 September 26 W. Argyll to Sir James Stewart concerning Heriot's Hospital, Edinburgh, Scotland, 1 page on paper, Hench # 24 (6435-a) (Box-folder 3:9)
  - 1664 September 26 Indenture with a calligraphic decoration for the first initial, between Matthew Grier, Matthew Grier the younger, and William Hale, 1 page, paper document, Hench #14 (6435-a) (oversize)
  - ca. 1664 "A Relation of the Success of the Love of King Henry IV to the Princess of Conde" by Sir William Beecher, concerning King Henry IV of France and Charlotte Marguerite de Montmorency, bound volume, 102 paper pages, many water-stained, Hench # 27 (6435-a) (Box-folder 3:10)
  - 1666 May 3 Sight Draft signed by Edward Sherburne, Clerk of the Ordnance, Jonas Moore, Storekeeper [Richard?] March, and [Francis?] Nicholl, on paper, Hench # 25 (6435-a) (Box-folder 3:11)
  - 1673 Legal document signed by Thomas Henshaw and mentioning Thomas Lyndfield, on vellum, Hench # 13 (6435-a) (Box-folder 3:12)
  - 1673 June Account of the Estate of John [Oliver?], administered by [Thomas Oliver], on vellum, signed by the registrar of the court, and listing payments to John Ingram, John Kent, Edward Ingram, George Oliver, John Martin, John Young, William Martin, Robert White, John Bunn, John Manning, Stedman Broaden, John Gordon, Sarah Ingram, and John Parrott, among others, on vellum, Hench # 14 (6435-a) (oversize)
  - [1673?] Rough Draft of an Indenture between [Nicholas Johnson?], Sarah [?], and [Edmund Warnoff?], 30 numbered pages with two blank, pages attached at top by a vellum cord, on paper, Hench # 29 (6435-a) (oversize)
  - ca. 1677 Sermons of J. Hickson, on paper, bound volume with brown covers, Hench # 32 (6435-a) (Box-folder 3:13)
  - 1678 Papers from the Lambarde Family Archive concerning the Titus Oakes Plot, including examinations, notes, etc., on paper, Hench # 5.b (6435-a) (Box-folder 3:14)
  - [1678] Articles of Impeachment against the Earl of Danby, Thomas Osborne, for high treason and other crimes (1632-1712), on paper, 2 pages on 1 l., Hench # 5a.8 (6435-a) (Box-folder 3:15)
  - 1684-1686 Bound Commonplace Book of Kinard De La Bere [d. 1733?], including "Remembrances for Servants," notes on precious metals, stones, and gems, including diamonds, tables of various weights and measures for various cities or countries of Europe, such as London, Dublin, Scotland, Cadiz, Castille, Seville, Barcelona, Gibraltar, Lisbon, Tunis, Constantinople, Smyrna, Messina, Aleppo, Antwerp, Rome, Florence, etc.; with a separate [William?] De La Bere document dated November 1749, both on paper, Hench # 30 (6435-a) (Box-folder 3:16)
  - [ante 1685?] Statement to "My Lords" concerning King Charles II want of monies, 3 pages on 1 l., on paper, Hench # 5a.6 (6435-a) (Box-folder 3:17)
  - [1690] Engraving (made in 1803) and signature of John Lowther, Viscount Lonsdale (1655-1700), Hench # 36 (6435-a) (Box-folder 3:18)
  - ca. 1690 Theological extracts in Latin and English, with a signature George Reynolds about midway through the volume, bound with 19th century boards with a calf backstrip and corners, on paper, Hench # 28 (6435-a) (Box-folder 4:1)
  - 1691 January 27 Indenture, Kent County, between Anne Powell, second daughter of Nathaniel Powell of Wiarton [Plat?], Boughton Mount Parish, and Thomasin Collins, [Cobtree], Allington, Kent County, signed by Anne Powell on the bottom of the page; with the words "sealed and delivered in the presence of Nathan Powell and Bart Dutton" and signed by Nathan Powell, Bart Dutton, and Anne Powell, on the verso, vellum, Hench #14 (oversize)
  - early 17th century Legal document signed by James Spurlinge, Sr. and James Spurlinge, Jr. and Henry [S. Clark?], in Latin on vellum, Hench # 13 (6435-a) (Box-folder 4:2)
  - [early 17th century?] Legal document, on vellum, Hench # 13 (6435-a) (Box-folder 4:3)
  - 17th century "A True Abstract or Calendar of the Statutes," in English and Latin, indexed, ca. 290 pages on paper, with about 159 numbered, apparently a signature [E. Baldwin?] at the end of the volume, bound in vellum, Hench # 33 (6435-a) (Box-folder 4:4)
  - 17th century Satirical Poem concerning Louis XIV of France and Madame de Maintenon, 2 pages on 1 l., paper, Hench # 23 (6435-a) (Box-folder 4:5)
  - [late 17th century?] Inventories of Lambarde family manuscripts, 4 items, paper Hench # 5a.9 (6435-a) (Box-folder 4:6)
  - [late 17th century?] Biographical Notes concerning the life and career of William Lambarde (1536-1601), 4 pages on 1 l., on paper, Hench # 5a.9 (6435-a) (Box-folder 4:7)
  - ca. 1708 Satire entitled "A dialogue between Sue and Kate two old women of Rippon about the death of Dr. Hawley with an account of his will and some other occurrences: and his legacies at his death,", 16 pages on paper, Hench # 40 (6435-a) (Box-folder 4:8)
  - [post 1714] "Project of a Treaty of Commerce with Moscovy" between Peter I, Czar of Russia and the King of Great Britain [George I?], 16 pages on paper, written in French, Hench # 39 (6435-a) (Box-folder 4:9)
  - [ante 1720] Manuscript Sermons of Luke Milbourne (1649-1720), Rector of St. Ethelburga's and lecturer of St. Leonard, Shoreditch, 73 numbered pages on paper bound in green leather covers, Hench # 31 (6435-a) (Box-folder 4:10)